[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right all right everyone we'll begin
uh
welcome to the stoa i'm peter limberg uh
the steward of the stowa and it still
has a place for us to coherent dialogue
about what matters most
at the nice edge of this very moment and
today we have kalia
young then she can like correct me if
i'm mispronouncing your name
also known as the identity woman and
today
is talk is going to be on internet
identity and our digital
cells um so how it's going to work um
kalia is going to present her thoughts
for about 20 minutes
um and then if you have any questions
throughout drop them in the chats
i will call on you to mute yourself you
can ask your question directly
if you don't want to be on youtube just
indicate that in the chats and i'll
read your question your behalf and we'll
we're here for 60 minutes total
so that being said i will take you in
and i believe you have a screen share
you gotta you gotta mute yourself
uh there you go oh we're playing again
thanks so much peter um it's really
great to be here
um so so
the the two things i'm going to talk
about today are both
internet identity and our digital selves
and they're inextricable
inextricably linked um
the first um question you know this is
this this forum is about philosophy and
so this question
what is identity is sort of at the heart
of
or a key philosophical question that's
been asked throughout the ages
and the answer that i like best
is that identity is socially constructed
and contextual so this means that
we together co-create what's real and
this applies both to the social meaning
of identities like whether it's being a
man or a woman
and everything in between and also to
the digital systems that we create
they aren't inherent they aren't just
the way things are
they are co-created by us and therefore
we get to shape them in the future and
that's what i've spent most of my career
on is
working on shaping how identity and
personal data are constructed in the
future
in the digital world so
on the one side you have identity
which are ways for people to connect to
other people and organizations
and on the other hand you have personal
data and
along with that tools to hold people's
personal data and support them managing
and control them
and i see these two concepts as
inextricably linked
yet somewhat separate where you can have
really in-depth conversations about
managing
identifiers and identity and those are
slightly separate from the ones around
personal data so i'm gonna
touch on both in this talk and then i'll
start with personal data
so identity is incredibly complex um
this is a a chart that was
done by some consultants working with
the australian government trying to
articulate
different contexts where people are
using their digital
identities um across their lives and
it's
it's it's all over
in fact it ends up touching um you know
sort of our interaction with
digital systems that put our identities
into databases
now now encompasses almost all
institutional interactions we have and
many personal ones because those are
happening in
mediated digital realms and personal
data is
vast i created this chart
um working with the world economic forum
in 2010 and 11 looking at
all the different types of personal data
that we have so we have
asset data about all the things that we
own
relationship data about all the people
we talk to and connect to
data about our educational history and
our work history
government records about us
including sort of vital statistics
and property ownership there's
health data so
the records we have with our doctors and
other institutions but also personal
tracking and then the insurance that
goes with that
communications data
activity data both what are we doing in
the physical world and what are we doing
in a digital world
content so what are we reading watching
listening to
along with all of our own private
documents that we're
generating and creating and then context
data
where are we in time and space and who
are we with
and then finally just really core basic
identity data so it's
it's huge
and then we have this question about in
the digital realm what happens to
to all these this whole range of
personal data and
these charts that i'm drawing on were
actually
put forward by the federal trade
commission in the united states looking
at issues around personal data and this
is how they
articulated what's happening today with
people's personal data
that individuals are the source of that
data
and it's um it's generated as they
interact with the internet
financial institutions their health care
providers
they go shopping or they interact in the
public realm
um this next ring is sort of the second
place that data lands with data brokers
um
that that then go on to aggregate the
data
and sell it to what they call data users
so
banks marketers the government
individuals law enforcement etc and
all of this data then that is being used
by these data users what are they doing
with it
they are taking it and affecting the
lives of
individuals right and so we're seeing
more and more awareness of it this chart
is
i think almost a decade old but now we
have
movies that have come out like the
social dilemma
sort of making the point even stronger
that
the data about people being used by
actors
is having impacts on people's lives
without their awareness or consent
this is that full chart
um and i this is another sort of
iteration of
of looking at the flow of data um
for an individual who's going shopping
on the internet
and um interacting with a retailer and
you can see i don't i think you can see
my cursor up here the data analytics
provider
the aggregated data set broker and the
marketer are all
trading data about the person that has
nothing to
it's not connected to the person it's
all disconnected and happening
in this realm that they can't really see
and have no control over
sorry so one way to think about
what's another way to sort of visualize
the set of issues around data
is that on the on the left hand side of
this
table you have the linkage to the
individual
with it being more and more con directed
linked directly to the individual and on
the other hand you have this
different sources of data so volunteer
data is things that i sort of
understand i'm doing like i'm typing a
tweet into twitter
or sharing a photo on flickr i have a
conscious awareness of like
sharing data into a system observed data
is
what time did i do that tweet
when did i cross the threshold of the
doctor's office
etc and then inferred data is data
that's taking volunteered and observed
data and making
inferences and that starts to get really
creepy like
and this is what they're doing with data
sets around elections which is like
based on data we can see about people
that they volunteered and that we
observe
what might we infer about how they might
vote or ha
you know do anything else
um and
different authors have written about
this i like daniel solov's
book very much the digital person
written in 2004
he says that the best metaphor to think
about these issues is in not
1984 where a sort of big government is
coming and controlling us but more like
kafka where we can't
actually see what's happening
because it's all so far away from us and
impacting our lives in ways that are
invisible and we can't really trace back
you have a series that the wall street
journal did
looking at um
you know the hundred top websites and
all of the tracking
um that's going on as we
navigate the internet so this is a key
place where data about us
is generated and shared and in all of
the apps on the app servers many of them
are also doing this
type of thing and increasingly with
internet of things and sort of sensors
um
filling out our environment there's more
and more
sources of this data and when when i
originally did
put this together i didn't even think
about um you know
alexa theory and google home but all of
those are in our homes if we let them
and they're collecting data about us
and so this data markets and the data
for sale just continues to grow
sort of out of control and it's uh it's
a big it's
it's it has big implications and it's
often sort of framed like this
very innocently like people's data is
being aggregated and exploited without
their knowledge and consent
it doesn't sound that bad but really it
should be like this
um where where it's
it's it's not good what can happen with
all this data
floating around um big data is
personal data and on the flip side
personalization and the type of things
that businesses are looking to do for us
require personal data but
there's this question about how do we
change things
in a constructive way how can we shift
to
have a relationship between customers
and businesses and brands that
isn't exploitive but
actually is generative and
respectful and imbued with dignity
and you know can we
create this world where individuals are
the center of their own data lives
and and i i believe we can um
i've been working to innovate the
protocols to represent people in the
digital realm
um in ways that empower and
and and put them in control
so i want to talk a touch on the other
piece of
of this venn diagram which is
identity and the ways for people to
connect to other people
and organizations so we're all used to
this
we get usernames and passwords to
log into various websites
but this puts us at the affect of those
sites
we're always underneath those domain
names
underneath those systems and whoever the
administrator of that system has the
power to
erase our accounts on those systems
and we also end up with potentially
hundreds of different accounts so this
isn't really a great solution
we could also imagine and these have
been created someplace as a public
center identity provider model where the
individual creates an account with the
state
and the state intermediates all of their
interactions with
a whole range of other institutions and
service providers and in fact this is
what
was proposed and in some ways has been
ruled out
in india with their aadhaar number
although the supreme court there sort of
limited private sector use the vision
that was
that was put forward by those creating
the system was that
you would use your ad hard to do almost
everything
across the public and private sector
and we have private sector identity
provider model where
we can log in with google and facebook
and amazon
and apple id but those large companies
are then
intermediating us we aren't in control
of our digital selves
we could get our own urls but we rent
those from the
domain name registrar that we register
them with and we could get our own
phone numbers and most of us have had
our phone numbers for
years if not decades but the problem is
we rent those too if we
stop paying our phone bills we lose our
phone number it's not actually ours
so we end up with the choice landscape
for identity is sort of like being
underneath these either private sector
name spaces
or pub you know global registries
itu-t runs the phone number system and
the dns system is for domain names
and if there are no digital identifiers
that we really own
can we control our digital identities
and personal data and the answer is
no so that's the first problem we have
to solve is how do we own and control
our digital identifiers
and that's that's what we've done with
the decentralized identity technologies
that i've worked on
and and and i'm a leader in developing
is create the tools and systems for
people to really
be able to be handed attributes from
authoritative sources and generate their
own
identity information and be a choice
about who they share it with
without it um being handed to them
without their identifiers being
controlled by
a centralized um
source a centralized
service or being chopped up into into
many little pieces
and then we can go from sort of you know
this was drawn
almost 15 years ago by a colleague of
mine trying to explain what we were
doing with this user-centric
identity movement is shifted so that we
are at the affect of
large companies to us being centered and
in control of our digital
representations of ourselves
and then to sort of close the loop and
go back to where we started
that i see there's a real opportunity
for new tools
that are emerging to support people
actually owning and holding and managing
the digital
their personal data so you have
the my data global community that is
organizing companies who have a
values-based
approach to supporting supporting people
collecting and managing this data
that they call my data operators they
just published a white paper about
this emerging set of this emerging sort
of class of
companies and then you also have work
that i
lead working on standardizing
secure data stores and and
encrypted data vaults for people to
manage
their their their data and
ultimately their digital identities
so with that i hope um i've shared a
as a starting place for our conversation
today about
the internet our identity and our
digital selves
and i i wanted to close with this final
um
sort of question where i that's
philosophically interesting
and and where i think the conversation
can go
in in a productive way within the
industry is what happens when we
understand the data as
body if we take um
what we understand about bodily autonomy
and think about
what it means for our digital twins or
digital
representations to be treated with that
same dignity and respect
as opposed to alternative models or
metaphors where
some are proposing that we see personal
data as property that can be bought and
sold
but we've decided we can't buy and sell
people
and we certainly aren't buying and
selling pieces of ourselves so why would
we be buying and selling pieces of our
digital representations of ourselves
and with that i will
stop screen sharing and we can go into a
discussion
all right um so start dropping your
questions in the chat i'll call on you
and just unmute yourself to ask your
question
um i'm curious uh just like a personal
background how did you get into this
how did you become the identity woman
yeah i mean um
i got started by um
connecting with a network in san
francisco called planet work
and in the year 2000 they hosted a
conference called global ecology and
information technology
and out of that network they spent 18
months considering
what would be a missing piece of
infrastructure that they could help
build
in the digital world that would enable
social environmental groups to cooperate
better
and they figured out that a missing
piece of infrastructure was how
people actually represent themselves and
called for the funding
of of the development of the open
standards for that
and the funders that they went to
couldn't understand what they were
saying even though they're like if you
don't do this we're going to end up 10
years in the future and governments and
corporations will own everybody's
digital representations of themselves
and they're like ah and here we are
facebook owns you know facebook and
other
networks own our representations of
ourselves and we don't
because they can terminate us without
recourse and
back to you know if we think of data as
body
there's a whole bunch of laws and rules
and norms
and around how i have bodily autonomy
and it's not okay for people to hurt
my body that's not true you know anybody
can
google could terminate my gmail account
any day
and i have no legal recourse even though
it's
a massive part of who i am and how i
interact in the world same with facebook
or linkedin or any of those things
so it's it's um so i've been on a
mission ever since then
and in 2005 we all needed cute names for
our blogs
and i was the only woman i'd met in
meetings about this topic
and i was like i guess i'm the identity
woman and then it sort of stuck
and um what is making you optimistic and
pessimistic about
you know this field emerging field that
you're working in
i'm really optimistic with
the the high performance collaboration
happening amongst a whole range of
actors in the industry to really get
these standards developed
so that it provides an infrastructure
layer
for us to own and control our digital
selves
um what am i pessimistic about
i think that we could end up going off
some
strange regulatory directions and not
actually get at the root of the problem
which is we need
open standards-based infrastructure to
sort of flip the paradigm
on google and facebook like it's not
enough to just quote unquote regulate
them
we have to innovate a new
we have to innovate around and support
the emergence of these new tools
that just like email allows anybody with
an email address to communicate with
none
one another or the standard like html
allow
the web to flourish we need this next
layer of the internet that's about
people and their data
to come into being and i'm a little bit
worried the regulatory
conversation could derail it or it could
be good for it but it's
kind of a
right um so let's uh
pivot to the chats uh doctor strange
loop you had a question if you're gonna
mute yourself yeah
oh that's kevin okay cool uh yeah uh hi
glia thank you um
so in the social dilemma uh i don't know
if you saw it but uh jerome
lanier characterized social media as
having deception at the core of every
interaction
because it was built upon a deceptive
advertising model where you're you know
selling
data and attention to um advertising
companies
um i'm wondering if you sort of agree
with this or
if like if it's possible to sort of find
authenticity
in a system like this as built upon
advertising and duplicity or
more general what's your view on like
the relationship between
between the intent behind a digital
space and the nature of the interactions
that are within it
so so i think that he's right
how the current social media companies
are architected
i think that the the tracking of
specific
individuals and individual targeting is
what's sort of gotten everything to go
off course
i think if you i think there are ethical
advertising models but they're more like
i've got my local bicycle that i
connect with in some social network and
oh there's bicycle shops in our
neighborhood that would like to
advertise it
with us to us because we're the bike
people
and that is a synergistic kind of mutual
mutually beneficial advertising
relationship that you could have where
the bike
club decides what local businesses it
wants to let
advertise to its members
so like all advertising isn't
bad but how it's being done with sort of
big data and sort of the underlying
stocking is very problematic
any uh follow-up questions doctor
um right so i guess what
you're sort of encouraging a more
sort of local
i mean so what would would that require
so there's sort of like there's one
there's an underlying thing like all
advertising is bad i don't agree with
that i think the current models
that are based on individual tracking
and profiling
and sort of stalking you around the
internet and targeting you for your
psychographic profile of you
is different than targeting interests
you may have that are shared by other
people
like the local bike club where there is
no need to
track you and build up a
virtual shadow version of you that is
then being targeted by
advertisers right so you're saying the
the
deceptive part isn't necessarily the
advertising it's
how the digital itself is being
collected
yes um another follow-up i guess
do you have any suggestions on how you'd
sort of go about
encouraging this more local
recommendation system without
creating this uh
this you know behemoth of tracking
software and creating this
giant digital profile because it seems
like you need to know some information
about the user
well you need to know yeah they're in
the bike club right like
it's not a lot of you know it's more
like it's just
shifting where how the targeting is
happening and
you know um duckduckgo has an
advertising model but doesn't know who
you are
it just knows what you search for right
so so
i think that um
and we we need to build future social
networks based on
open protocols so there's one that i
know of called true.net
um some friends of mine who literally
they founded planet work which is the
organization i got started with all of
this 20 years ago
to really put um the best of what
they've learned into practice to
understand how we can build
tools for people to connect that provide
relevant
traceable information in terms of
tracking where it's come from to get to
you
and also um i'm not i don't think
they're going to have an advertising
model but it's
there i could i can see ethical
advertising models i don't want to erase
it completely off the internet and say
there should be none ever it's just
the deep profiling of people in the
psychographic targeting that's
shaping elections is toxic and bad
thank you all right maybe gray you're up
next
all right so i i apologize up front
for being like overwhelmingly cynical
um but i i do just
really feel very curious about why
something so user-centered would ever
exist in a world where individuals
are on the wrong side of an enormous
power imbalance
with corporations and governments
i'm just curious how uh
how this would get picked up and
implemented in the real world
it's like really exciting that we can
come up with models that are more
ethical
but who is going to use them when
they're going to make more
money being shady
right so this is where i actually think
you know there's a saying in the data
broker industry that
is half the data is wrong we just don't
know which half
right and that actually if we
um you know when these mod
when these systems and models were
created beginning
really in the 60s and going gangbusters
in the 70s
where you had presidential commissions
in the united states asked
you know sort of motivated by people
getting catalogs out of nowhere they're
like why do they want me to go
fishing well because there's these data
brokers collecting all these databases
and giant mainframes about people
and the us actually went through a whole
kind of
uh machinations about like a
government-held national database of all
the data about all the people and they
put in a bunch of laws to prevent that
from happening what they didn't really
address was like
the private sector side besides like
some wishy-washy things like privacy
principles
but now nobody was really envisioning a
future where we would have little
computers in our pocket okay so now that
i have a computer in my pocket
this is an equalizing force if
we then build the tools that center me
and go okay i'm going to collect my data
in my own personal cloud and my own
little data bank
and i'm going to have the right to
license pieces of it
and i'm going to have the tools to
connect in a peer-to-peer way with my
like why does facebook own our social
graph
because our social graph is a commons
that we as people co-created
well the great news is my digital
identity community
has built protocols where software i own
and software you control can connect us
without a company
intermediating us yeah the company that
wrote the software intermediated us
but if we use open standards it means i
can switch software providers
and and this is why i'm like been a kind
of like
open standards open standard open
standards because it shifts the paradigm
and gives us a
a level playing fluent field a pl
a non-commercial
non nobody owns it
basis to build those new things on which
some of those models will be commercial
and some won't be
but until we have open standards
you can't flip the switch and
disintermediate the large companies that
own both the software
and our digital identities and are
intermediating everything
on our behalf so
i hope that right so if i if i
understand you're right it's like if we
open the digital borders then
individuals will have
like digital mobility like they've never
had before and that'll be hugely
empowering
i think that's awesome thanks so much
yeah
all right i'm gonna read this question
on behalf of rick um
i want to learn more about the
decentralized identity solutions
you have worked on how does a
decentralized system incentivize
validators to provide what is mostly
seen as public good
who pays for these systems that's a
great question
so i i chose not to dive into the weeds
of these decentralized identity
systems um because there's a lot of
information about them and this is a
philosophy talk not a technology how to
talk
um so one of the key things to
understand about these infrastructures
that i'm working on is it's not the
institutions somehow vanish and we're
all just decentralized floating in outer
space
but that the
[Music]
those institutions can do what they are
good at and not what they shouldn't be
doing so
i was born in british columbia the
government of british columbia is the
authoritative source of my birth date
i don't make it up it comes on a little
piece of paper
that might you know from the chain of
things that happened after my parents
filed the paper with
them and i get a thing called a birth
certificate so that is an
authoritative source of my birthday now
i would love the government of british
columbia to give me a digital version of
that piece of paper
so that i can share with other people
who are really interested in
my birthday because it's interesting for
other purposes like
getting a passport or getting a bank
account and all the sorts of things i
need to
have a birthday for it to do but
in the architectures we had before the
decentralization
the only way for that to happen would be
for somehow every place i wanted to
share my birthday to connect back to the
province to ask them directly in a
digital connection what was true about
me
and that's a privacy nightmare and in
fact the government leaders in british
columbia have been leaders in this field
of decentralized digital identity
because they're like yeah we're the
authoritative source of all the people
born in our provinces
for their birth date but we do not want
to know every time they go and buy
alcohol
or open a bank account or do anything
else because that's none of our business
so how do you thread the needle and
support
the thing that they are authoritative
for and not
them being in the middle of all of my
transactions and you need this
decentralized architecture to support
them issuing me a verifiable credential
which is like a digital a digital
version of the paper thing
and that that verifiable credential i
have the power to hold it in my own
wallet
just like i could hold a tiny version of
my birth certificate in my wallet
and i could present it to
the what we call the verifiers or the
institutions that i need to share it
with
and and that i'm the locust of control
for sharing that information and so
that's where the decentralization comes
from
i think there's some confusion with sort
of all the the blockchaining world and
sort of like
public keys and crypto and like
that's different than what um we're
talking around
decentralized identity architectures
all right um
captain identity you had a question
you're unmute
yeah i have several questions but like i
think the one related for you
is has there been any progress since
since we signed a copenhagen letter and
wanted more control of our data and
stuff like that what's the copenhagen
well you're not familiar with that that
was signed in copenhagen 2017
of many people who who worked with
wikipedia foundation and stuff like that
to actually
uh this is petitioned to take control of
our data
so i'm i'm all for nice words on paper
i've worked in the trenches with the
technical communities trying to build
this
[Music]
so yeah i mean if you look at my data
global and the
my data operators paper you know it's
tangible you know there's 48 my data
operators they've identified which is
companies
attempting to create architectures
based on a different paradigm of
you know sort of right relationship with
our data and we'll see where it goes i
think
um i think that the
institutions whether we like it or not
wikipedia is an institution on the
internet
uh wikipedia mozilla and the internet
archive
you know who's been leading some of the
dweb work have not really grasped
the importance of open standards as as
the
the sort of opportunity switch
and i they haven't they are absent from
the
communities from the internet identity
workshop that i lead and the community
is working on this so i think
you know maybe it's up to us to do more
education around the potential of these
open standards but now that they're more
real and tangible i think that case is
easier to make
yeah so so where is the progress this
year do you know any
if we want to drive this forward where
should we go to make progress in this do
you know anything you want
come to you're welcome to come to my
conference which is coming up in two
weeks the internet identity workshop
another forum that i highly recommend is
the my data global community
they're um very active
literally around the world um with um
they were founded in finland so they
have a
a lovely nordic flavor to them but if
we're gonna have you know global
leadership on this why not from the
nordic countries who
have you know led in in many social
sectors
um and they
are really trying to
shift the paradigm at least within the
european
context away from just quote unquote
data protection
which is like fine if you're trying to
protect people from their data getting
sucked up into giant databases which is
where
those frameworks are coming from from
the 70s and 80s
and we need to talk about this world
where we're in now where i have a
computer in my pocket how am i empowered
with my data
with institutions i trust to help me
and not be just exploited because
protection isn't enough we need to shift
the paradigm
and get it so that it's useful and
helpful and makes my life better and our
communities lives better
and and that's you know what i see my
data global being
a key organizational force trying to
drive that forward and make it happen
tangibly in the world
that's cool thanks all right
uh daryl you have a question hey
thanks for doing this um is there a
go-to space where an average
user of the internet can go to to
start dealing with this issue like
learn to use duckduckgo or is eff doing
anything and true.net i couldn't find
them
oh it's it's t-r-u okay
um no e um
the um so that's a great question
um so one organization that's trying to
to support consumers having better
information is the me to be alliance so
i would say they're
you know very much a compliment to the
my data global
community and and they're they're
connected
um there is a company i just interviewed
them on my
podcast i think it's um priv p-r-i-i-v
so they have a free app that you can
download that like
walks you through all the things you
should be doing as a consumer
and then if you want to
they have this sort of package of
privacy assistance
tools you can buy from them which is
cheaper than going and buying all those
apps separately
um so that's a tool but
again that's coming from the protection
framework of how do we sort of fight the
badness now
and and how do we build the future and
my data global
has individuals belonging i mean part of
it was to bring the consumer side and
the
business side together so that you would
have consumers who want to use the apps
that these new these emerging companies
are building
andy follow darryl nope okay
uh lara you had a question
yeah thanks um so
i'm an entrepreneur and i create a lot
of educational content
and i'm i've been so
fed up with um traditional social media
platforms and yet
this is great timing because i was just
like i'm getting off all of them
and yet like what's the alternative
right i don't find
them particularly effective um
and so i've been dreaming into
alternatives where
we can really create authentic community
owner content
is there anything like that that's in
the works
already um and then a second
part is like just your thoughts on more
ethical
and effective platforms for really
building connection
yeah um so i think that um
i think that the um the the fetiverse is
an interesting starting point as an
attempt to do this so the fetiverse is
the networks built around mastodon
which is like open source
twitter facebook and you could spin up
your own mastodon server
and get your friends to join it and talk
with them there
um but it also has limitations and that
the sort of naming conventions are kind
of clunky
if you left one server and went to
another all your links would break and
your stuff wouldn't move with you
so i think um you know you're you're
making me think i should convene
a you know some sort of especially
focused
convening around this question of now
that we have
i think of what my community's been
building as like lego bricks
right you've got decentralized
identifiers and verifiable credentials
and j-link and
did com and like there's now a bunch of
open standards-based lego bricks and now
the question is how can entrepreneurs
like you
pick them up and build cool things with
them and
because they're open standards based
means they connect with other things
that are also
based on those open standards and we
have a flowering of
you know thousands and thousands of
different social networks and tools
based on these open standards and that's
what i hope can happen in the next
couple years
and i'm really thrilled that you're
dreaming into what could be
and i love you know one option is to
come to iiw and say i have these big
dreams help me build them because it's
an unconference so anybody can put
whatever they want on the agenda
um but also you know i i think another
place to go if you're an entrepreneur
looking at this and sort of exploring
the edges of the future is the deweb
community so this is being led by the
internet archives
they've had several summits over the
last few years
they're not particularly focused on open
standards because they don't think they
understand the impact that they will
bring once they
succeed but nonetheless there's
that's where the people who are trying
to build something
different or hanging out
any follow-up question nope okay
margaret you had a few questions
yeah um so
my first question which i don't know
that i can articulate it in the form of
a question
but um some of what you're
talking about here around open source
technologies
has me wondering if like
there's a whole other part of this
conversation that is
missing and maybe i'm sure you're aware
of it but maybe you're just not
presenting it here around
how intellectual property works and
like the normalizing of what we consider
normal property rights
um yeah and that like that's a deeply
entrenched incentive system
that seems like it uh
you know goes against open source on
every level
so i've i in our conversations haven't
really used the word open source
there is a distinction between open
source which is the
code being open so i did say mastodon
it's open source but that's the code
base
and then it's part of what it does is it
speaks a set of open
standards-based protocols called
activity pub
right so open standards are
descriptions of how computers talk to
each other
and two different computers with two
different code bases can use
protocols and open standards to connect
to each other
and that's what's the critical piece
i think you're right about the paradigms
around
um intellectual property and how
we've you know the origins of that go
back to like how books
books were originally copyrighted and
licensed and then that has translated
into every media form since
i think that um
creative commons license is you know an
interesting attempt to
break the worst of those things
um and i think it's also you know
copyright as we understand it has also
gotten
instances like you know is the data
about me
copyrightable because it's my
quote-unquote ip
well this is this problem because like
my data about me
if we think about that leads us down
some problematic
avenues in the law um
a frame that folks are talking about
that i like is thinking about data as a
resource
and looking at resource law and how
you know the laws around how we share
water in our rivers
are maybe a better sort of route of
law and legal precedent to think about
how do we manage these flows of data
about our society as a collective good
that we need to know stuff about what's
going on um
but i agree with you i i think you know
these questions of
how are the intangible things
the intellectual things how are those
governed is really you know
really big questions that we need to
think about and
maybe do differently in the future
thank you for that distinction between
open source and open standard i missed
that and that's key
and that feels a lot more scalable in
terms of
convincing someone to build that into
their existing
um product of like
okay you don't actually have to release
your your proprietary code but you can
build something on top of it that allows
it to speak to others
um that feels like okay that's a hill we
can all climb
yeah can i ask one other follow-up
question
um which is around
pedagogy which i think daryl kind of
touched upon this in his question
but i guess i'm just curious um
that this feels like a really important
conversation to be having so it's
exciting to hear
that you are working on this and that
there's a whole community of people who
are
focused on these questions um but i
i know i encounter a lot of people who
just don't seem aware
of like the
power of information or their own
potential agency within the digital
space
and seem to lack a really basic
understanding
of like what
digital information even is or digital
infrastructure and how that relates or
connects to their own personal use
of software and of these services and so
i'm curious if
i know you pointed out some places where
like one could go
if they were already inclined to think
about okay what should i be doing as a
consumer to protect myself
but how do we bring this to the
awareness of more people of like that
this is a conversation to be having and
that
you know you what like what are you
giving up to just watch cat videos on
youtube
you know like what what's the trade-off
here like what are what's actually
happening
yeah i mean i think that i mean this is
why the social dilemma
has been you know as problematic as that
film is it's helpful
the great hack also does a good job of
articulating this so i think
you know when i started talking about
these problems
facebook didn't even exist and those
we'd be like
well these things called social networks
are coming and then they're gonna track
you and then that's gonna be a problem
and people are like what are you talking
about i'm like
okay just trust me now i don't have a
problem explaining all that stuff
but i literally was talking about these
things 15 years ago and
it was i feel like you're gonna have a
digital self and how do you control it
and they're looking at me like
what so i think that
you know as much as it is a problem like
people don't get it they're starting to
go oh
oh oh we're manipulating elections we're
having mass misinformation we're
you know there's now like real tangible
social
problems coming from our lack of
foresight in in designing this next
layer of the internet
um and i think
that i actually don't think we quote
unquote make people care
i think innovative entrepreneurs
responsible governments are going to
build the next generation of
digital tools to operate differently and
we're already seeing that happen so you
have you know ironically enough
it's banks and governments who are the
most interested in the decentralized
identity technology
and from the government side it's coming
from
western liberal democracies who
understand they have a responsibility to
give their citizens
information that they are authoritative
for but really
do not want to be in the middle of their
citizens lives
and so they're they're literally funding
they're funding startups to build
products and forcing them to
interoperate before they pay them
so that they actually get working
standards so we'll see
i mean i think it comes with new
products that work better for people
because if i control my own data and
then i go and interact with businesses
who are interacting with data that is
for sure about me
instead of half the data being wrong
because they're stalking me around
in aggregating data behind the scenes
and building digital shadows without my
awareness
they're just interacting with me and my
data
under my terms in ways that potentially
are really empowering and cool
and i think you can actually make more
money that way like i actually think
that there is this sort of place we can
get to
if we can get enough um
you know capital and funding to go that
direction um
that that is just better and it wins not
because it's
good although that's like yay it
probably will be better
it wins it's it's actually
better for business and better for
people i mean i've also heard that ad
tech as we know and understand it is
going to
collapse and in fact it's being
regulatory attack and
everybody still wants to do business
okay so how do we
do it ethically and in a new paradigm
that doesn't
erase data but shifts sort of how it's
managed and
and working for people and businesses
thank you for just shifting that from a
social problem to a design challenge
that feels like a really
useful framework to kind of attack it
from versus like this like
educational moral emotional thing um
yeah thank you yeah all right
uh so we'll have one more question maybe
gray
if you can bring us home
uh yeah i actually i i feel like my
question's like a nice like
little like outro question um
maybe i'll rephrase it slightly given
that occasion but what
what feelings do you hope that those of
us who are gathered here today leave
having um learned a little bit more
about our
data and our information um what what
frames
would you hope that we can take with us
uh to keep us from
merely being frustrated frustrated and
overwhelmed by the situation
i don't know i mean um
i feel i don't want to say i feel
frustrated and overwhelmed like i use
all these tools
too i mean i've never really i
technically have a facebook account but
i can't use it it makes me
feel ill um i do use twitter
but twitter actually never twitter was
always up front about what it was doing
right it was doing micro blogging that
was public
it didn't change halfway through
um
you know and adjust privacy settings and
this is like
um but
um
i don't know i mean i think
to me the best antidote has to sort of
it's been to get
into the weeds with my technical friends
and work to help
shape the future because i believe it's
shapeable
like that's that's also like true like
back to what how we started this it's
socially constructed and contextual
literally we make it up right and so i'm
in the trenches leading the secure data
store working group
which is um you know
deeply tactical and i follow the
technical bouncing ball as best i can in
that leadership but it's
tangible like a year from now or
whatever we're gonna have this open
standard for a data vault for people to
hold their data
great okay that's like a critical brick
in the lego bricks that we need to build
this alternative world and that's where
i
find my optimism and i'd love to you
know people
listening and listening to this leader
like
please join the party if you have any
inclination
that's we can't build it alone and
there's so much work that's
that's that's now happening that could
be built upon
and used that i'm really hopeful so i
don't know
yeah i hear you it's like you can make a
difference and if you can't make a
difference other people are making a
difference it's not hopeless
right and like and you know i would say
like be
an early adopter right like start
patronizing
businesses and tools that are trying
something different give them feedback
file bug reports like do
something that's helping the people
trying to shift the paradigm right
awes awesome thank you so much thank you
awesome so uh we're almost at the hour
uh
any kind of final words you'd like to
close with where we can find you what
you're doing now
sure um i left my um
i left my email in i don't see it i left
my email in the chat
um you can find me at identitywoman.net
and the internet identity workshop
happens every six months
so the next one's in a couple weeks but
if you missed that we'll be
doing it again in april and
you know participate in my data global
conference it's a really awesome
community i'm speaking on two different
panels there
and you know get involved
awesome uh so i'll make some closing
announcements in a moment but kalia
thank you so much
for coming to the stoat today that was a
lot of fun
so upcoming events uh i'll plug uh this
one right here a community during covid
creating an unlowly planet
jillian richardson uh she she wrote the
book the unlonely planet uh it's kind of
a building relationship basically what
we're doing here at stoa
so i'm happy that she's gonna be coming
in um maybe gray you have a
event on sunday if you want to maybe
mention that one
yeah cody and i are hosting raw
relationships so it's the next
installment in the in the raw series
we're going to be talking about
what draws us into romantic
relationships
why we find them so devastating when
they break down
and what keeps us trying after every
fresh heartbreak
to to find that special somebody
cody and i feel like this is just
absolutely on our own edge
we are so not ready to have this
conversation and so
we would be very grateful if you come
and enter this like
space of uncomfortable mushy sad
happy feelings and discover something
about love with us so that's going to be
on sunday and
i really hope to see some some familiar
faces from this room there
beautiful and those those conversations
have been so fun like these raw
conversations if we haven't on
sunday and maybe you have another one
the existential kink maybe just kind of
related
if you want to plug that out as well
yeah sure yeah that's uh later on this
month
i'm going to be talking to carolyn
elliott who is the author of existential
kink
which is a fantastic my absolute
favorite book on shadow work
uh so if you if you want to learn how to
just like just bask in self acceptance
of even the parts of yourself that you
have hated the most for the longest time
ever oh my goodness
uh that that is something that she would
be more than happy to teach you how to
do
uh at the existential king session i'm
very excited for that one it's gonna be
very spicy
so as you can see here kalia we're
pretty weird and eclectic
at the stoa um
so you can find our website uh the
stoa.ca
um the patreon website and the sub stack
there that being said everyone thanks so
much for coming to seoul today
thank you